Guide to the Farnam Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Farnam family papers
1721-1941
MS 203
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
150
Correspondence, diaries, letterbooks, financial papers, writings, scrapbooks, and memorabilia of the Farnam family of New Haven, Connecticut, 1721-1929. The papers of Henry Farnam (1803-1883), and two of his sons, Henry Walcott Farnam (1853-1933) and William Whitman Farnam (1844-1929) form this collection. The papers of Henry Farnam include personal and professional correspondence concerning his family, life in New Haven, and the building of several canals and railroads in Connecticut and the Midwest. Materials documenting the New Haven and Northampton Company, Chicago and Rock Island Railroad, Mississippi and Missouri Valley Railroad, Northern Indiana Railroad, and Peoria and Bureau Valley Railroad is arranged here. The papers of Henry Walcott Farnam include personal and professional correspondence, financial papers, writings, subject files and scrapbooks relating to his family, life in New Haven, student and teaching experiences at Yale, membership in local, state, and national academic and reform organizations, and philanthropic activities on behalf of educational and charitable institutions. The papers of William Whitman Farnam include correspondence and topical files relating to family matters, Yale University, and New Haven Park Commission activities.
Farnam family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Henry W. Farnam estate, 1934 and later additions. Gift of Louise Guion and Elizabeth K. Harvey, 2003, and Louise Guion, 2004.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Henry Farnam, 1721-1898. II. Henry W. Farnam, 1841-1941. III. William W. Farnam, 1860-1929.
Scope and Contents
The Farnam Family Papers contain the correspondence, diaries, letterbooks, financial papers, writings, scrapbooks, and memorabilia of the Farnam family of New Haven, Connecticut, 1721-1929. The papers of Henry Farnam (1803-1883), and two of his sons, Henry Walcott Farnam (1853-1933) and William Whitman Farnam (1844-1929), form this collection. The papers of Henry Farnam include personal and professional correspondence concerning his family, life in New Haven, and the building of several canals and railroads in Connecticut and the Midwest. Materials documenting the New Haven and Northampton Company, Chicago and Rock Island Railroad, Mississippi and Missouri Valley Railroad, Northern Indiana Railroad, and Peoria and Bureau Valley Railroad are arranged here. The papers of Henry Walcott Farnam include personal and professional correspondence, financial papers, writings, subject files, and scrapbooks relating to his family, life in New Haven, student and teaching experiences at Yale, membership in local, state, and national academic and reform organizations, and philanthropic activities on behalf of educational and charitable institutions. The papers of William Whitman Farnam include correspondence and topical files relating to family matters, Yale University, and New Haven Park Commission activities.
The papers are arranged in 313 boxes, totalling 150 linear feet. The collection is organized in three series: I. HENRY FARNAM, 1721-1898; II. HENRY W. FARNAM, 1841-1941; and III. WILLIAM WHITMAN FARNAM, 1860-1929.
SERIES I, HENRY FARNAM, 1721-1898, contains the correspondence, railroad papers, diaries, and financial papers of Henry Farnam, an engineer, railroad builder, and philanthropist. Correspondence and Letterbooks include material detailing Farnam's extensive business career with the New Haven and Northampton Company (canals and railroads), the Chicago and Rock Island Railroad, the Mississippi and Missouri Valley Railroad, Northern Indiana Railroad, and the Peoria and Bureau Valley Railroad. Farnam supervised much of the construction of the Chicago and Rock Island Railroad, including the design of the first railroad bridge across the Mississippi River. Railroad Papers include account books, financial papers, payroll data, cost estimates, surveying material, land claims, cashier's records, vouchers, and other material detailing the planning, construction, and financing of many railroads. Letters with numerous railroad employees and officials elaborate upon the daily activities involved in railroad construction. (See: Letterbooks)
Correspondence and Letterbooks also include personal letters with several family members and friends, including children, brothers, and his wife Anna Sophia Whitman Farnam. Other correspondents include Noah Porter, Chauncey Goodrich, and Joseph E. Sheffield.
Diaries contains volumes written by Henry Farnam and his wife. An 1830 diary is that of George Theodore Kingsley and describes his student life and activities at Yale. Henry and Anna Farnam's diaries contain remarks on family and business matters.
Financial Papers consists of account books, bills, and deeds relating to family expenses and property. Material pertaining to the family home on Hillhouse Avenue in New Haven and for Sheffield Farm are also available.
SERIES II, HENRY W. FARNAM, 1853-1933, contains correspondence, letterbooks, financial papers, writings, subject files, and scrapbooks of Henry Walcott Farnam, an economist and professor at Yale University. Academic, political, financial, and personal interests are documented in these materials. As an active member on the boards and executive committees of many educational, academic, and charitable organizations, Farnam participated in policy decisions and financial campaigns.
General correspondence and Select correspondence contain incoming letters from family members; colleagues at colleges and universities throughout the United States and Germany; many social reform organizations and figures; a variety of New Haven and national charitable and educational bodies; local, state, and national political figures; and Yale University officials and employees.
Letterbooks (boxes 202-207) contains copies of outgoing correspondence to these individuals and organizations. These volumes are indexed and include letters to such individuals as: Simeon Eben Baldwin, Samuel Clarke Bushnell, William Henry Carmalt, James Lewis Cowles, Edward Salisbury Dana, Franklin Bowditch Dexter, Chauncey Goodrich, Arthur Twining Hadley, John Koren, Francis E. Leupp, John Punnett Peters, Noah Porter, Alfred Riggs, Thomas Lawrason Riggs, Carl Schurz, James Rockwell Sheffield, William Graham Summer, Horace Dutton Taft, and Booker T. Washington. Among the organizations and associations. represented in Farnam's letters are: the American Academy of Political and Social Science, American Economic Association, American Missionary Association, Calhoun Colored School (Calhoun, Ala.), Civil Service Reform League, Hampton Institute, Hopkins Grammar School, Indian Rights Association, Lowell House, Morning News, New Haven Hospital, Tuskegee Institute, Yale-China Association, and other Yale University organizations.
His writing, teaching, business, and philanthropic interests are documented through materials relating to alcohol and Prohibition, civil service reform, the labor movement and public welfare, the use of tobacco, World War I relief work, New Haven and its development, and United States politics and government. Writings includes drafts and material for Chapters in the History of Social Legislation, and course materials includes lectures on the modern labor movement, public finance, and social politics. Additional files contain lecture notes from his studies in Germany and articles and speeches written from 1871-1933. The latter include items written while a student at Yale and in Germany, and range from academic, to political, economic, and historical topics. Speeches to a wide range of groups are arranged here as well (boxes 235-241), with audiences including students at Yale-China functions and many gatherings of New Haven area residents.
Subject files consists of correspondence, notes, printed material, and miscellanea relating to Farnam's academic and literary research interests, family history, Yale University, and many of the organizations and associations he supported through membership and financial contributions. The largest quantities of material concern alcohol, civil service reform, Hopkins Grammar School, Lowell House Association, Morning News, Yale Review, Yale University, Class of 1874, and tobacco.
Scrapbooks contains several volumes of newspaper clippings and memorabilia relating to the personal and professional life of Henry W. Farnam. Volumes organized under the heading "Yale University" include material from Farnam's undergraduate years and his work on behalf of the Yale Bicentennial, Class of 1874, and Yale Review. Other volumes contain material relating to examination papers, Lowell House, New Haven Hospital, and World War I relief appeals.
SERIES III, WILLIAM WHITMAN FARNAM, 1844-1929, contains the papers of William W. Farnam, a Yale graduate (B.A., 1866), lawyer (Columbia, LL. B., 1871), trustee of Yale University (1885-1891), treasurer of Yale University (1888-1899), and member of the New Haven Commission of Public Parks (1880-1014). This series is arranged in two sections: Correspondence and Topical files.
Correspondence includes select files for letters from Timothy Dwight, family members, William Howard Taft, and from individuals associated with the New Haven Park Commission and the Yale Bicentennial.
Topical files includes material relating to Susan W. Farnam, William's wife, and financial papers.
Biographical / Historical
The Farnam family first settled in Connecticut in the person of Henry Farnam (1803-1883). Farnam engaged in the engineering and building of canals and railroads in Connecticut, and supervised the construction of the Chicago and Rock Island Railroad and the Missouri and Mississippi Valley Railroad in the Midwest. His eldest son, Henry Walcott Farnam (1853-1933) was educated at Yale University (A.B., 1874; A.M., 1875) and in Germany. He taught political economy and economics at Yale, served on many national boards and commissions, authored numerous articles and books, chaired the Yale Review (1892-1911), and was an active national reformer in the areas of civil service, prohibition, and tobacco use. He also supported many educational institutions, Indian missionaries, and charitable organizations in the United States.
William Whitman Farnam (1844-1929), also a son of Henry Farnam, studied at Yale (B.A., 1866), in Germany, and received his law degree from Columbia in 1871. His college societies were Linonia, Kappa Sigma Epsilon, Alpha Sigma Phi, Delta Kappa Epsilon and Skull and Bones. He was one of the Spoon Committee and a member of the Varuna Boat Club. After graduation he spent three years in Europe; studied at the Universities of Berlin and Heidelberg, receiving from the latter degree of J.U.D. He entered Columbia College Law School in 1869 and was graduated with degree of LL.B. in 1871. He began practice in 1873 in New Haven. He was trustee of Yale University from 1885 to 1891; treasurer of Yale University from 1888 to 1899, and director of National New Haven Bank from 1888 to 1900. He was a member of the New Haven Commission of Public Parks from 1880 to 1914, serving as its vice-president and president; first president of the Connecticut Branch of the American National Red Cross, and for many years a member of the Central Committee of the National Organization. He was a trustee of the Sheffield Scientific School, and a trustee of the Peabody Museum. He married Miss Susan Frances Strong, June 4; 1873, youngest daughter of late General William K. Strong of New York city.
Morning News; Alcohol -- Law and legislation; Business; Charities -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Civil service -- Study and teaching; Economics; Families; Hospitals -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Indians of North America; Prohibition; Public welfare; Railroads -- United States; Social sciences; Tobacco; Working class; World War, 1914-1918; Chicago (Ill.); Connecticut; Europe -- Description and travel; Germany; Middle West; Civic improvement -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government; Account books; Deeds; Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Authors; Businessmen; Capitalists and financiers; Educators; Political scientists; Aiken, William Appleton, 1907-1957; Andrews, Charles A.; Asakawa, Kan'ichi, 1873-1948; Atwater, Edward E. (Edward Elias), 1816-1887; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1830-1907; Baldwin, Simeon E. (Simeon Eben), 1840-1927; Beers, Thomas H.; Bigelow, Poultney, 1855-1954; Bingham, James S.; Bouton, J. M.; Bowles, Samuel A.; Brady, John Green, 1847-1918; Burnham, John B. (John Bird), 1869-1939; Bushnell, Samuel Clarke, 1852-1930; Carmalt, William H. (William Henry), 1836-1929; Chittenden, R. H. (Russell Henry), 1856-1943; Colby, James Fairbanks, 1850-1939; Collins, Charles; Collins, John Churton, 1848-1908; Cowles, James Lewis, 1843-1922; Daggett, Leonard Mayhew, 1863-1949; Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1849-1935; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Day, Clive, 1871-1951; Depew, Chauncey M. (Chauncey Mitchell), 1834-1928; Dexter, Franklin Bowditch, 1842-1920; Dodge, Nathan P.; Durant, Thomas Clark, 1820-1885; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Eaton, Daniel Cady, 1834-1895; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926; Ely, George B.; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943; Farnam, Henry W. (Henry Walcott), 1853-1933; Farnam, Henry, 1803-1883; Farnam, William Whitman, 1844-1929; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Frelinghuysen, Frederick T. (Frederick Theodore), 1817-1885; Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Goodell, Thomas Dwight, 1854-1920; Goodrich, Chauncey, 1836-1925; Graves, Henry Solon, 1871-1951; Greene, George Walton; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Grinnell, Josiah Bushnell, 1821-1891; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Halstead, William S.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943; Henry, John; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Hooker, Thomas, 1844-1922; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Hume, Edward H. (Edward Hicks), 1876-1957; Kingsley, William Lathrop, 1824-1896; Koren, John, 1861-1923; Leupp, Francis E. (Francis Ellington), 1849-1918; Lewis, Henry Gould, 1820-1891; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909; Paine, Robert Treat, 1835-1910; Peabody, Francis Greenwood, 1847-1936; Peters, John P. (John Punnett), 1852-1921; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Reed, Samuel B., 1818-1921; Riggs, Alfred; Riggs, T. Lawrason (Thomas Lawrason), 1888-1943; Ripley, Alfred Lawrence, 1858-1943; Ruggles, Charles; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906; Seligman, Edwin R. A. (Edwin Robert Anderson), 1861-1939; Sheffield, James R. (James Rockwell), 1864-1938; Sheffield, Joseph E. (Joseph Earl), 1793-1882; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1838-1913; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910; Taft, Horace Dutton, 1861-1943; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940; Trumbull, Lyman, 1813-1896; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915; Watrous, Geo. H (George H.); Weir, Irene, 1863-1944; Weir, John F. (John Ferguson), 1841-1926; Whitman, William H.; Wilder, Amos Parker, 1862-; Woodruff, Clinton Rogers, 1868-1948; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Farnham family; Keep family; Porter family; Schwab family; Whitman family; American Academy of Political and Social Science; American Economic Association; American Missionary Association; Board of Research Associates in American Economic History; Boardman Trade School (New Haven, Conn.); Calhoun Colored School (Calhoun, Ala.); Carnegie Institute of Washington; Chicago and Rock Island Railroad Company; Civil Service Reform League; Cobden Club (London, England); Colby Club; Hampton Institute; Hopkins Grammar School; Indian Rights Association; Lowell House (New Haven, Conn.); Mississippi and Missouri Railroad Company; National Civic Federation; National Civil Service League; New Haven & Northampton Railroad; New Haven Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); Peoria and Bureau Valley Railroad Company; Tuskegee Institute; Union Pacific Railroad Company; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1874; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Connecticut Hall; Yale University. South Middle College Restoration Committee; Yale-China Association
- HENRY FARNAM (1803-1883), 1721-1898; Series I; 37 linear feet (88 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in five sections: Correspondence, Letterbooks, Railroad Papers, Diaries, and Financial Papers.
  Correspondence and Letterbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  Railroad Papers are arranged by the individual railroad company, and alphabetically by type under each railroad company.
  Diaries are arranged by individual, and then in chronological order.
  Financial Papers are arranged alphabetically by type.
  - Correspondence
    - 1721-1848 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - 1849-1851 (Box 2, Folder 14-22)
    - 1852 January-July (Box 3, Folder 23-36)
    - 1852 August-October (Box 4, Folder 37-48)
    - 1852 November-1853 February (Box 5, Folder 49-65)
    - 1853 March-June (Box 6, Folder 66-80)
    - 1853 July-November (Box 7, Folder 81-97)
    - 1853 December-1854 February (Box 8, Folder 98-110)
    - 1854 March-May (Box 9, Folder 111-126)
    - 1854 June-December (Box 10, Folder 127-145)
    - 1854-1855 December (Box 11, Folder 146-160)
    - 1856 January-1857 April (Box 12, Folder 171-178)
    - 1857 May-December (Box 13, Folder 179-193)
    - 1858 January-1858 August (Box 14, Folder 194-208)
    - 1858 September-1859 April (Box 15, Folder 209-221)
    - 1859 May-December (Box 16, Folder 222-234)
    - 1860 January-September (Box 17, Folder 235-244)
    - 1860 October-1861 August (Box 18, Folder 245-256)
    - 1861 September-1862 July (Box 19, Folder 257-269)
    - 1862 August-1863 July (Box 20, Folder 270-284)
    - 1863 August-1864 November (Box 21, Folder 285-301)
    - 1864 December-1865 December (Box 22, Folder 302-320)
    - 1866 January-December (Box 23, Folder 321-333)
    - 1867 January-1868 July (Box 24, Folder 334-353)
    - 1868 August-1869 July (Box 25, Folder 354-368)
    - 1869 August-1870 December (Box 26, Folder 369-386)
    - 1871 January-December (Box 27, Folder 387-393)
    - 1872 January-1873 February (Box 28, Folder 394-411)
    - 1873 March-December (Box 29, Folder 412-426)
    - 1874 January-December (Box 30, Folder 427-438)
    - 1875 January-December (Box 31, Folder 439-456)
    - 1876 January-December (Box 32, Folder 457-475)
    - 1877 January-December (Box 33, Folder 476-493)
    - 1878 January-December (Box 34, Folder 494-508)
    - 1879 January-December (Box 35, Folder 509-523)
    - 1880 January-December (Box 36, Folder 524-538)
    - 1880 January-December (Box 37, Folder 539-553)
    - 1882 January-September (Box 38, Folder 554-571)
    - 1882 October-1883 September (Box 39, Folder 572-587)
    - 1883 October-December (Box 40, Folder 588-595)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1854-1860 (Box 41, Folder 596-598)
    - 1860-1863 (Box 42, Folder 599-600)
    - 1866-1870 (Box 43, Folder 601-607)
    - 1870-1875 (Box 44, Folder 608-612)
    - 1875-1883 (Box 45, Folder 613-614)
    - 1883-1890 (Box 46, Folder 615-617)
  - Railroad Papers
    - New Haven and Northampton Company
      - Account books, 1836-1850 (Box 47, Folder 618-620)
      - Conductor's reports, 1849-1850 (Box 47, Folder 621)
      - Financial papers, 1826-1848 (Box 47, Folder 622-624)
      - Financial papers, 1849-1850 (Box 48, Folder 625-634)
      - Financial papers, 1851 (Box 49, Folder 635)
      - Payrolls, 1849-1850 (Box 49, Folder 636-637)
      - Printed material, 1850 (Box 49, Folder 638)
      - Surveying material, 1849-1851 (Box 49, Folder 639-641)
    - Chicago and Rock Island Railroad
      - Account books, 1850-1858 (Box 50, Folder 642-647)
      - Account books, 1853-1861 (Box 51, Folder 648-652)
      - Account books, 1858-1861 (Box 52, Folder 653)
      - Drawings and maps (Box 52, Folder 654)
      - Estimates
        - General, 1851-1854 (Box 52, Folder 655-661)
        - Fencing-Final, 1851-1854 (Box 53, Folder 662-666)
      - Excursion registers, 1854 (Box 53, Folder 667-668)
      - Financial papers, 1851-1852 (Box 54, Folder 669-678)
      - Financial papers, 1852-1853 (Box 55, Folder 679-687)
      - Financial papers, 1853-1855 (Box 56, Folder 688-696)
      - Financial papers, 1855-1857 (Box 57, Folder 697-704)
      - Financial papers, 1858-1861 (Box 58, Folder 705-712)
      - Financial papers, 1861-1881 (Box 59, Folder 713-719)
      - Memorabilia, undated (Box 60, Folder 720-727)
      - Payroll, 1852-1853 (Box 60, Folder 721-727)
      - Payroll, 1853 (Box 61, Folder 728-733)
      - Payroll, 1853-1854 (Box 62, Folder 734-739)
      - Payroll, 1854 (Box 63, Folder 740-745)
      - Payroll, 1854-1855 (Box 64, Folder 746-751)
      - Printed material, 1854-1855 (Box 65, Folder 752-757)
      - Surveying materials, 1851-1855 (Box 65, Folder 758-760)
      - Surveying materials, 1851-1855 (Box 66, Folder 761)
      - Vouchers
        - F-Z, 1852 (Box 67, Folder 762-769)
        - A-H, 1853 (Box 68, Folder 770-777)
        - I-R, 1853 (Box 69, Folder 778-786)
        - S-Z; Miscellanea, 1853 (Box 70, Folder 787-799)
        - A-C, 1854 (Box 71, Folder 800-804)
        - D-M, 1854 (Box 72, Folder 805-812)
        - N-Z; Miscellanea, 1854 (Box 73, Folder 813-821)
    - Mississippi and Missouri Valley Railroad
      - Account books, 1855 (Box 74, Folder 822)
      - Bills, 1854-1856 (Box 74, Folder 823-824)
      - Cashier's statements, 1856-1857 (Box 74, Folder 825)
      - Correspondence, 1855-1860 (Box 74, Folder 826)
      - Estimates, 1856-1859 (Box 74, Folder 827)
      - Financial papers, 1854-1862 (Box 74, Folder 828-831)
      - Land claims-Iowa, 1855 (Box 75, Folder 832-833)
      - Mississippi Bridge Company, 1854-1858 (Box 76, Folder 834-835)
      - Printed material, 1853-1861 (Box 76, Folder 836)
      - Propositions, 1854-1855 (Box 76, Folder 837)
      - Ward vs. Mississippi and Missouri Railroad, 1859 (Box 76, Folder 838-840)
    - Northern Indiana Railroad
      - Bills, 1851-1852 (Box 77, Folder 841-842)
      - Contracts, 1851-1852 (Box 77, Folder 843-848)
      - Estimates, 1851 (Box 77, Folder 849)
      - Estimates, 1851-1852 (Box 78, Folder 850-854)
      - Financial papers, 1851-1852 (Box 78, Folder 855-856)
      - Payrolls, 1851 (Box 78, Folder 857)
      - Printed material, 1850 (Box 78, Folder 858)
    - Peoria and Bureau Valley Railroad
      - Account books, 1853-1855 (Box 79, Folder 859)
      - Estimates, 1853-1854, undated (Box 79, Folder 860-862)
      - Financial papers, 1853-1861 (Box 79, Folder 863-866)
      - Printed material, 1862-1863 (Box 79, Folder 867)
      - Vouchers, 1853-1855 (Box 80, Folder 868-872)
    - Union Pacific Railroad
      - Financial papers, 1862 (Box 80, Folder 873-874)
      - Printed material, 1862-1863 (Box 80, Folder 875)
  - Diaries
    - Kingsly, George Theodore. (Box 80, Folder 875)
    - Farnam, Henry (1803-1883), 1830-1882, undated (Box 81, Folder 876-883)
    - Farnam, Ann Sophia Whitman, 1886-1895 (Box 81, Folder 876-883)
  - Financial papers
    - Account books, 1850-1873 (Box 82, Folder 884-888)
    - Account books, 1874-1884 (Box 83, Folder 889-892)
    - Bills, 1850-1875 (Box 84, Folder 893-897)
    - Bills, 1850-1890 (Box 85, Folder 898-906)
    - Deeds
      - Connecticut, 1874-1881 (Box 86, Folder 907)
      - Illinois, 1857 (Box 86, Folder 908)
      - Iowa, 1854-1881 (Box 86, Folder 909-913)
      - Miscellaneous, 1857-1874 (Box 86, Folder 914-916)
    - Hillhouse Avenue home
      - Architects, 1870-1874 (Box 87, Folder 917)
      - Bills, 1870-1874 (Box 87, Folder 918-922)